<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="xml"?>
<book xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>TRiCYCLE Manual</title>
        <author>
            <orgname>TRiDaS Team</orgname>
            <address>
                <city>Ithaca</city>
                <street>Cornell University</street>
                <postcode>14853</postcode>
                <country>USA</country>
            </address>
            <email>info@tridas.org</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <chapter>
        <title>What is TRiCYCLE</title>
        <para>TRiCYCLE is a universal dendrochronology file format converter. It currently has
            support for reading and writing 17 different file formats:<itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Belfast Apple</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Belfast Archive</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Besancon</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>CATRAS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Comman Separated Values (CSV)</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Corina Legacy</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Excel</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Heidelberg</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nottingham</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Sheffield</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>TRIMS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>TRiDaS</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Topham</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tucson</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Tucson Compact</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>VFormat</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>WinDENDRO</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>For a complete discussion of TRiCYCLE and its underlying libraries please see: Brewer,
            P., Murphy, D and Jansma, E (in review) TRiCYCLE: a universal dendro data conversion
            tool. Tree-Ring Research.}</para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>Installation</title>
        <para>TRiCYCLE is a Java application and so can be installed on any modern operating system.
            To make installation more familiar though we have packaged it up into native installers
            for Windows, Mac OSX and Linux. Download the relevant package for your operating system
            from the <link xlink:href="http://tridas.sf.net">SourceForge</link> website.</para>
        <para>
            <variablelist>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Windows</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Run the setup program and follow the steps. The program will be
                            installed to your hard disk and shortcuts added to your start menu. If
                            you do not have Java installed on your system or you do not have the
                            required version the installer will provide you with assistance to do
                            so.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>MaxOSX</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>Open the .dmg file in Finder. Drag the TRiCYCLE.app file into your
                            Applications folder, or wherever you'd like it installed. MacOSX comes
                            pre-installed with Java so there is no need to install it
                            separately.</para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                    <term>Linux</term>
                    <listitem>
                        <para>An Ubuntu deb package is provided for TRiCYCLE. Install this package
                            with your standard package manager (e.g. dpkg). It includes information
                            on all the dependencies required including Java therefore it should
                            install everything you need if you are running Ubuntu. On other
                            distributions you may find that the dependencies do not install
                            automatically and the TRiCYCLE installation fails. If this is the case
                            you will have to install the following dependencies
                                        manually:...<inlinemediaobject><imageobject><imagedata
                                        fileref="../main/resources/icons/512x512/application.png"
                                /></imageobject></inlinemediaobject></para>
                    </listitem>
                </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>
        </para>
    </chapter>
    <chapter>
        <title>How to use TRiCYCLE</title>
        <para>The first step is to specify the format of your input file(s). Choose the your format
            from the pull down list on the File List page. Then select the file(s) that you'd like
            to convert by clicking on the browse button. You can add files one at a time or in bulk.
            Once you have your list of files prepared you can then go to the Convert tab.</para>
        <para> On the Convert page, the first thing you need to do is select the desired output
            format from the drop down list. Next, press the convert button and after a short delay
            your files should appear in the list below. At the bottom of the window, you'll see a
            summary showing how many files were processed, how many of the convertions failed and
            how many were converted successfully but with warnings. </para>
        <para> The results of the conversion are shown in a tree view on the convert tab. Each file
            that convered successfully and with no warnings is shown with a green tick icon, below
            which are shown the output file or files. Files that failed to convert are highlighted
            by a red cross along with a message explaining what went wrong. Depending on the input
            and output formats chosen, a input file may be converted into one or more output files
            as some formats can store just one series while others can store multiple series. </para>
        <para> If there were warnings produced during the conversion process, then the file will be
            marked with a orange exclamation icon. Warnings can be associated with either the
            process of reading the input file, or writing the output file. They can also be related
            to a single series within the file or the input file as a whole. The warning messages
            are displayed to illustrate the context of the warning. Longer warnings will scroll of
            the edge of the window, but if you hover your mouse over the warning a tooltip will show
            the entire message. </para>
        <para> If you would like to preview the result of the conversion process you can double
            click on the output files and they will be displayed in a text viewer. This option is
            not, however, available for binary formats such as CATRAS and Excel. </para>
        <para> Once you are happy with the results of the conversion you can save the files
            permanently to disk by pressing the save button. It will offer you the option of
            specifying which folder to save the files to. </para>
    </chapter>
</book>
